If you saw a wooden long ship crashing
through the North Atlantic,
you might assume you were watching a
historical reenactment, but
this actually happened in the year 2000.
For centuries, historians dismissed
the sagas of life, Erickson reaching North
America as pure folklore.
They looked at the 3000 miles of violent
freezing ocean between Scandinavia and
Canada and concluded the journey
was scientifically impossible.
Skeptics argued that a clinker built ship
constructed by overlapping wooden planks
instead of joining them edge to edge,
would simply splinter under the force of
the open ocean. To test that theory,
an Icelandic captain named Gunner Marl
Gerson spent two years building an exact
replica of a ninth century GDA ship.
He named his new vessel the East Lending
Gore on Iceland's, national Day Gerson,
and a crew of eight cast off from
Reykjavik. They imposed strict rules on
themselves. No engines, no modern GPS
navigation and complete reliance on 10th
century technology to cross the sea, to
validate the historical text they had to
subject themselves to the exact physical
reality their ancestors faced a millennium
ago, leaving the safety of the coastal
shelf, the crew entered the deep Atlantic,
a landscape entirely stripped
of visual landmarks.
Without a magnetic compass, they relied
entirely on sensory navigation. This meant
reading the specific rhythm of the ocean,
swells and calculating their latitude
based on sun angles during the day and
star positions at night, harnessing the
wind with a single massive square sail.
The ship proved remarkably efficient,
cutting through the water at a steady
speed of seven knots. But speed alone
wouldn't save them.
As they approached Cape Farewell at the
southern tip of Greenland, they entered a
region notorious for generating some of
the most violent localized weather
systems in the Northern Hemisphere.
A massive storm system trapped the crew
for 10 straight hours. They faced
blinding rain.
Towering swells and plunging
temperatures fighting constantly
to keep the open hole from taking on
water. Here, the very designed
skeptics criticized kept them afloat.
The overlapping clinker planks
allowed the hole to flex and bend with
the waves rather than remaining rigid and
snapping under the immense pressure
emerging from Cape Farewell Intact
proved that a Viking
long ship was an incredibly sophisticated
piece of maritime engineering,
built specifically to absorb the
ocean's punishment.
When the clouds finally broke, the crew
cited the imposing jagged coastline of
Greenland making landfall at
Broda height. This specific fjord holds
massive historical weight.
It was the ancient home of Eric, the red
and the exact staging ground life
Erickson used for his own westward push.
The ruins of the original North
settlements here feature thick earth and
walls and turf roofs. Reflecting a
culture deeply adapted
to harsh, unforgiving environments, a
survival philosophy directly mirrored in
the ship's construction. After resting
and repairing their rigging, the crew
left Greenland in late July to make the
final push across the Davis Strait
toward Canada. They eventually
dropped anchor at Lonzo Meadows in
Newfoundland.
This is the globally recognized
archeological site confirming a Nors
presence in North America, hitting
these precise historical coordinates with
period accurate tools. Confirmed that the
transatlantic route of the 11th century
was a deliberate, repeatable,
navigational achievement. With the
toughest ocean crossing behind
them, the physical survival mission
evolved into a cultural victory lap down
the North American eastern seaboard.
Sailing past the rugged isolated
communities of Newfoundland and Nova
Scotia, the ship provided a living link
between modern maritime residents and the
continent's earliest European explorers.
For the thousands of people lining
the docks, watching a thousand year old
myth materialize in their own harbors was
a striking, visceral experience, but
the most arresting visual of the entire
expedition was still waiting for them
at the mouth of the Hudson River. On
October 5th, the East Lger sailed
directly into New York Harbor.
The wooden mast and handwoven sail stood
in stark contrast against the towering
steel of the World Trade Center.
The ship then drifted past the Statue of
Liberty, aligning the very first European
explorers to reach
the new world with its
most recognizable modern emblem. Over
4,200 nautical miles, captain Gerson
and his crew defeated freezing
temperatures, massive storms, and the
crushing weight of the open Atlantic
by risking their own lives to recreate
the voyage, they erased the doubts of
the skeptics and anchored
the Viking sagas into undeniable human
history. To learn more about
the ship, the crew, and their place in
maritime history, explore the exhibits at
Viking World.